<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hypocrisie discovered, or, A further manifestation of the secret designe, practices, and inventions of the Protector, so called, to seat himself in and be vested with, the power and office of chief magistrate in this nation, contrary to those many declarations, engagements and protestations in opposition thereunto, not onely as it was contrary to an act of Parliament, made after many out-goings of God, against the late King and his monarchy, but also as it did oppose the kingdome and interest of our Lord Jesus</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45295</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3887</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7532</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13513530</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13513530</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99865</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45295)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99865)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 791:43)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Hypocrisie discovered, or, A further manifestation of the secret designe, practices, and inventions of the Protector, so called, to seat himself in and be vested with, the power and office of chief magistrate in this nation, contrary to those many declarations, engagements and protestations in opposition thereunto, not onely as it was contrary to an act of Parliament, made after many out-goings of God, against the late King and his monarchy, but also as it did oppose the kingdome and interest of our Lord Jesus</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:99865:1"/>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99865:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
HYPOCRISIE DISCOVERED: OR, A Further Manifeſtation of the ſecret Deſigne, Practices and intentions of the <hi>Protector,</hi> ſo called, to ſeat himſelf in, and be veſted with the Power and Office of chief Magiſtrate in this Nation, contrary to thoſe many De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations, Engagements, and Proteſtations in oppoſition thereunto, not onely as it was contrary to an Act of Parliament, made after many out-goings of God, againſt the late King and his Monarchy, but alſo as it did oppoſe the Kingdome and Intereſt of our Lord Jeſus.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Iſa. 29. 15, 16.</bibl> 
               <hi>Wo to them that ſeek deep to hide their Councel from the Lord, and their works are in the dark, and they ſay, who ſeeth us, and who knoweth us. Surely your turning of things up-ſide-down ſhall be eſteemed as the Potters clay, &amp;c.</hi>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>BEing a little affected with the ſence of the diſhonour brought upon the Name, Works and wayes of God, the pretious Cauſe and Intereſt of Chriſt, and his poore people at this day; and that therein many as I hope truly fearing God are conſenting and drawn aſide by the deceiving of the Protector (ſo called) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hrough the too high eſtimation and good o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion they have of that perſon, for ſuch being dealt with for ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his hands in this way of his own chooſing, they will acknowledge his turning ſhort upon former profeſſions, whereby Saints w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re engaged, and his apparent evill in his acceſſion to, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> worſe adminiſtration of the Government. But yet defend themſelves with a hope (their advantages in ſiding and pertaking with him, tending to blinde their eyes) that there may be good intentions and integrity at the bottome; forgetting (as is to be feared) that the appearance of evill is to be avoided, and not the leaſt committed, for the greateſt good; And though I am far from taking plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to rake into the Sores and Infirmities of any, knowing ſo much of my own; yet for the Lord his work and Peoples ſake, to reſcue the feet of ſome and prevent others from falling into his ſnare; yea for his ſake alſo, if the Lord ſo pleaſe to bleſſe it (with whom private applications have not prevailed) the lancing of a putrified ſore being neceſſary, and in order to its Cure: I have thought it my duty, therein alſo, I truſt, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the minde of the Lord, who is making his folly manifeſt unto all, that he may proceed no further, a little in ſome particulars to open him and his wayes.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:99865:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>HYPOCRISIE DISCOVERED, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>IT might be remembred with what cheerfulnes of heart out of love, to the Lord &amp; his work (when the laſt invaſion was from <hi>Scotland,</hi> many of the choiſeſt ſpirited Saints, came out of ſeverall parts of the Nation to ingage againſt them; What their entertainment alſo was from the Army, thoſe at <hi>Warrington bridge</hi> very well know. The new Moddel was never ſo ſlighted, ſcorned and reproached by the old Officers, and Army as theſe were; who inſtead of receiving acknowledgement for their ſo ſeaſonable appearance in the common-ſervice; were returned under as great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, as could be poſſibly laid upon them: <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Its worthy to be obſerved, that this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity (now more heightned) in ſome Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers and others of the Army, againſt that ſpirit (now more refined) which then appeared in theſe godly perſons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to ſhew it ſelf, not only at</hi> Warring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton-bridge, <hi>but alſo when M. G.</hi> Harri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon <hi>was with his Horſe in</hi> Scotland, <hi>which was ſome time before.</hi>
               </note> The good People bearing all with meekneſſe and patience, unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to harbour a hard thought of him, who yet gave countenance to all the unworthy dealings they met with. Upon his return from the Battell at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> ſeverall Perſons (eminent for godlineſs) of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations in and about <hi>London</hi> came to him, as to acknowledge the Lords goodneſſe in that his wonderfull appearance, ſo alſo that he would im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy his utmoſt endeavours with the Parliament, for the further improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it to anſwer the Lords deſigne, and the great expectations upon the hearts of his people. <note n="*" place="margin">When ſome complained of the ſo long de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lays of buſines in the Parliament, In an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer thereunto; he did declare there was not above ſix men (if ſo many) in the Houſe that had a heart (or minded) to any thing. And when ſuch told him that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was very requiſite a period ſhould be put to their ſitting; and others more fit, to be choſen in their rooms, and that the moſt publique ſpirited people of the Nation did much deſire it: This he could not but acknowledge ought to be ſo; yet did ſo fear that honeſt ſpirit which preſt after it, that he durſt not venture to go about it, leaſt the power coming too much into their hands, he ſhould be hindred of what we may now perceive he had then propounded to himſelf. And therefore did go on with the Parliament, though they had not a heart to do any thing till ſuch time (as is well mentioned) they begun to entrench upon him; the plain truth is, there was ſuch juggling (in the letting them ſit ſo long, afterwards diſſolving them; in chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Little Parliament, and ſome of them contriving to bring the Power to him) that it would take up too much time and paper to declare it.</note> To which he replyed amongſt other things, that there was no more hopes of drawing on the Parliament there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto then was of making a Bar of Iron become a Lute ſtring; but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired that they with the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to which they did relate, would ſeek unto the Lord, to know his pleaſure in what was to be done and to let him know, what upon ſuch ſeeking ſhould be ſet upon their hearts, which accordingly they did; and waiting again upon him, gave this as the ſum of what had been ſet upon them. That though they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:99865:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to acknowledge the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in thoſe many worthy things, wherein it had pleaſed the Lord of his grace to own them; yet were they perſwaded, that he had cut them ſhort of ſpirit to the reſidue of his work; and therefore did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that a ſhort time of ſix Moneths or thereabouts might be put, beyond which the Parliament might not ſit, and in the interim care to be take for qualifications of perſons to be elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſucceed in the Government; which might be furniſhed by the Lord, for the carrying on of his work, whereupon by very harſh (not to ſay re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viling) ſpeeches, he ſoon diſcovered that he was altered from what he ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be when formerly they had been with him, being fallen with ſome of the grandees of the Parliament, by whoſe means as was then feared and as ſince evident ground is given to judge, he hoped to bring about ſome ends of his own, and ſo ſlighting them and the advice ſo ſolemnly brought unto him, having formerly ingaged them to aske councel from the Lord, they were diſmiſſed; but left this behind with him to pauſe upon; That ſeeing he would not hear, they would turn unto the Lord, whoſe ears are alwayes open to the cryes of his People: And its obſervable that hence forth inſtead of improving the Talents God had put into his hands for advance of his Work, the good of his People and the whole Nation, he rather put himſelf into a contrary courſe appearing with an uncontrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable violence for the carrying on the Act of Oblivion to ingratiate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, which effectually he did) with that generation, from whom all our troubles aroſe; wherein was forgiven to them; three times more then would have paid many poor and well-affected; the mony due to them upon Publique Faith, (which in the Parliaments ſtreights had been ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced) and other publique debts, and they put into a capacity of oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their well affected Tenants and Neighbour, as by ſad experience hath been found, beſides many other miſchiefs that Act produced; and though there wanted not thoſe who in love and faithfulneſs, deſired to deal with and perſwade him to deſiſt his violence in that which was to gratifie the common enemy, and grieve the Saints and well-affected: he turned the deaf-ear to all, laying hold upon every thing that tended to pleaſe the multitude, rather then the good People of the Nation (and termed them a diſcontented blood thirſty people, that would never be ſatisfied till they had raked out their bowels,) living at a rate far above the ordinary ſphear, carrying it yet faire with the Parliament; who would not deny him (or rather from whom he would not be denyed) any thing wherein
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99865:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
he appeard, untill it pleaſed the Lord to engage us in a War with <hi>Holland,</hi> which thoſe who were chiefly entruſted with the management of it, (I mean the Commiſſioners for the Admiralty and Navy) endeavoured to carry on effectually, and ſo as might not increaſe the charge of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, and to that end reported their opinion to the Parliament, that (the work now lying at Sea) the defect of a ſufficient number of Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairing men might be ſupplyed out of the Land-army, which accordingly was done once or twice; but this continuing, he eaſily perceived would eclipſe his greatneſſe, and indeed fruſtrate his deſigne of ſetting up himſelf, and 3000. more of his Army being voted to go to Sea, he (who before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viled the Meſſengers of ſeverall Church for but mentioning that the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament ſhould ſet a ſhort time for their own ſitting, and ſo go off with honour) with a Junto of his Officers reſolves the diſſolving of them, which is accordingly put in execution, but under a very ſpecious pretence as by the Declaration of the Army upon that occaſion, and by his Speech to thoſe who ſucceeded in government appears, which compared with theſe his after actions too manifeſtly declares that all was but a Vizard to cover his ugly deſigne of enſlaving the Nation to his luſt; whereby (which is the bitternes of it) is brought ſuch a reproach upon the Name, Wayes and people of God, as none but himſelf in reſpect of his high profeſſion was capable of bringing the like.</p>
            <p>The Parliament being diſſolved, In a ſhort time after, the ſupream Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority (by him and his officers is put into the hands of a certaine num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of perſons in an extraordinary manner brought together for the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe thereof, as appeares by his ſpeech to them, who at their firſt meeting wanted a name (and many yet are to ſeek what to call them) though after debate by a Vote of the major part (for they themſelves divided about it) they were called (though very unlike to it) a Parliament: He with the Councel that had mannaged affaires in the intervale were called to ſit with them, which all but himſelf and M. G. <hi>Lambert</hi> accepted of; Good people who rather ſuſpect themſelves then others (could not give way to any jealous thought of him) Judged his ſtaying away was that he might not greaten himſelf, rather then that it was in order thereunto; but though he abſented himſelf from the Parliament: where (to uſe his own terms) he would have been rendred very cheap (unleſſe his ſincerity to the worke and cauſe of Chriſt appeared) ſome there honoring men ſo farr as they honor the Lord, (and having mens perſons no further in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration (yet he failed not to ply the Councel where buſineſſes of greateſt concernment were tranſacted, which he kept much under his own girdle, and wanted not a daily account of what paſſed in the Parliament from his Brothers, Allyes, Officers and others, whoſe endeavour it was upon ſome pretence or other to obſtruct every good buſineſſe that came into de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, and ſo to render all their endeavours ineffectual for anſwering the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:99865:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
great ends of their aſſembling, and beget ſome colourable ground of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning the power into his own hands, That meeting (as the ſequel de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated) being deſigned, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtirrop for him to mount into the Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, and all things being prepared in a morning (two hours at leaſt ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier then ordinary) theſe get together into the Parliament-houſe and with as much gravity as for mality, move the reſigning the power accordingly, but this as early as it was, met with oppoſition, ſo that they durſt not hazard a vote in it, but ſneakingly withdraw without vote or adjourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to any other place or time, leaving a conſiderable number behinde, who were ſoon turned out by Muſqueteers and the afore ſaid run-aways ſubſcribe a thing called a reſignation, which is as ſignificant, as if ſo many Porters or other perſons had met to ſet up one of their own chooſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: This reſignation (contrived in private and ſubſcribed at White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall) being brought to him (as one ſurpriſed in the buſineſſe) cals upon his innocent Officers to go together, and pray that he might be guided what to do in it; And ſince upon occaſions hath made very ſolemn Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations of his ignorance in it, untill the reſignation was brought to him, though its well known, he was acquainted with the contrivance long before. And himſelf had ſpoken to Sr. <hi>Gilbert Pickering</hi> to go to a meeting where the thing called the Government was framing, which alſo was read to him before the diſſolution of that aſſembly; and the day before, (even the Lords day at his houſe) were met of his Brothers, Allyes, Officers and dependents, about the number of forty, who there agreed their early meeting at the houſe the next morning, to vote (as is aforeſaid) the tranſlating <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> him, but they fayling, by the oppoſition they met with, his Souldiers were ready to force, what by fraud the others could not bring about. The vaile being now taken off, he ſits down in the Seat of them (to wit, the late King and his race, whom the Lord had plucked up, and preſently appears acting their Principles, caſting off the work of God, ſeeking nothing but his own ſettlement: for which he knew in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon he had laid a good foundation by the Act of Oblivion, and other po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular Acts; but eſpecially by ſetting the edge of his Power againſt the poor deſpiſed people that had been faithfull to the Lord and his work in the former wonderfull diſpenſations, and reproaching thoſe honeſt hearts of that Aſſembly (called the little Parliament) who were turned out of the Houſe as enemies to Magiſtracy, Miniſtry, and Propriety, becauſe they agreed not to gratifie him in his luſt.</p>
            <p>The firſt conſiderable fruit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Government, after he had ſworn to govern according to Law, and the Paper called the Inſtrument of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is contrary to them all, the impriſoning Mr. <hi>Feake,</hi> Mr. <hi>Powell,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Simpſon,</hi> perſons unſpotted in their lives and converſations, all Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and labourers in the work of the Goſpel, and ſuch as are not inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to many in the Nation, having been eminently owned by the Lord in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:99865:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
his work, much more of the like nature after appeared M. G. <hi>Harriſon,</hi> Col. <hi>Rich,</hi> M. <hi>Cary,</hi> Quart. M. G. <hi>Courtney,</hi> M. G. <hi>Overton,</hi> Cornet <hi>Day,</hi> Mr <hi>Spitle-houſe, John Jones,</hi> Col. <hi>Allured,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to this day remain in priſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom no crime is objected, but its ſaid they may have their Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty if they will, though when that is inquired into, it cannot be, unleſſe they will engage to the preſent Government; which is contrary to their conſciences, to acknowledge him as an authority, much leſs a rightful Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority over them, and which is worſe, to binde them up from follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lord, how ſignall ſoever his appearances ſhould be: With all haſt, alſo in order to ſettlement at home, the peace muſt be concluded with the Dutch, and that upon tearmes ſufficiently diſhonorable, after all the eminent appearances of the Lord, in every engagement; leaving the guilt of bloud, in a very great meaſure, at the door of this Nation; which both the long ſitting and the litle Parliamen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> did abhor to aſſent unto, being throughly ſenſible that the finger of God, and not their luſt had led them into that war, but this muſt be done alſo under fair pretence of having peace with Proteſtants, that the more vigorouſly a war may be carried on againſt Antichriſt, but was not this to make himſelf wiſer than God, and indeed is it not plain, that the meaning of it was, that he might have ſhips and men to bring home gold from the Indies, whereby as he had ſet up himſelf, ſo he might maintain himſelf in deſpight of all; and this being blaſted, the return of gold failing, no ſtone muſt be left unturned, for getting it nearer home, the good and well-affected will not be deluded by him; and now he that would not be diſſwaded <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arrying on the Act of Oblivion (though told that thereby he would be caſt out of the hearts of good people, which he himſelf confeſſed, that he thought it would tend much thereunto) with a high hand unjuſtly and unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly breaks the ſame, to raiſe a revenue, whereby he may be enabled further to oppreſſe them and others. This together with his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>educing the forces, and abridging their pay for his own ends, and ſelf preſervation, which he would never be drawn unto for the ſake of the Lord, his work, and the Nations eaſe, doth evidently to half an eye declare by what principle he acted. Upon the ſame ground and principle <hi>(Jeroboam</hi> like, whatever is pretended) the National Parochiall Clergy, in their corrupt and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian ſtanding and maintenance; are upheld and impoſed upon the good people of this Nation, and the ſucceſſion thereof provided for, in a way as bad if not worſe, then that which derives it ſelf through the Papa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and of this he greatly boaſts in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> page of his firſt Speech to the Parliament, as a bleſſed fruit of Government, to put a ſtop to that heady way (as he phraſes it) of every one making himſelf a Preacher. When he hath been often heard in <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> but eſpecially up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Pencland</hi> hils in <hi>Scotland,</hi> at <hi>Glaſcoe</hi> to the Presbytery there, and at <hi>Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> when he would maintain laymens preaching in oppoſition to the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:99865:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Scots that ſpoke againſt it, to urge that ſcripture, <hi>Num.</hi> 26.27, 28, 29. where word was brought to <hi>Moſes</hi> that <hi>Eldad</hi> and <hi>Medad</hi> propheſied in the Camp, and that <hi>Moſes</hi> (though his ſervant deſired him to forbid them) did ſay unto him envyeſt thou for my ſake: I would all the Lords people were Prophets, and that the Lord would put his ſpirit upon them; and as <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> did judge his ſervant to be of a ridgid narrow ſpirit, becauſe he would have them forbidden propheſying; ſo himſelf judged the Scots and Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians to be of the ſame ſpirit, who would ſpeak againſt laymens preaching, of which ſee move in a Book intituled, <hi>Several Letters and Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages between the Lord Gen. Cromwell and the Governour of Edenburgh Caſtle, with the Miniſters there, Page</hi> 10 Let the Saints and Churches (even all that fear the Lord in theſe Nations) well weigh thoſe his words, its to be fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red he can turn himſelf into any ſhape, as may beſt ſerve his deſignes; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving formerly ſaid of the Earl of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> would never be well ſo long as he kept thoſe hedge Prieſts about him, reflecting upon Mr. <hi>Aſh</hi> and Mr. <hi>Good,</hi> perſons of approved gifts and grace, who then waited upon his Lordſhip: yea, let this be compared with his Speech to the little Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, <hi>fol</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> But when it came to other tryals as in that of Wales, which I muſt confeſſe for my own part, I ſet my ſelf upon; if I ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form what diſcountenance that buſineſſe of the poor people of God there had, who had watchings over them: Men like ſo many Wolves, ready to catch the Lamb aſſoon as it was brought into the World; how ſignally they threw that buſineſſe under foot, to the diſcountenancing of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt people there, and to the coun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enancing of the Malignant party of this Commonw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>; I need but ſay it was ſo, many have f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lt it by ſad ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, who will better impart that buſineſs to you, which for my ſelf and fellow Officers, I think was as perfect a tryall of their ſpirits, (mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the old Parliament) as any thing, it being known to many of us, that God hath kindled a ſeed there not to be parralleld, ſince the Primitive times of this ſeed are thoſe, that have lately declared againſt him, by their Paper intituled, <hi>A Word for God, or a Teſtimony on Truths behalf,</hi> to which the Reader is referred for further ſatisfaction. Now its needfull you ſhould know what that buſineſſe in Wales was, that he would have you underſtand, met with ſuch oppoſition from that Parliament, as mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred occaſion to him and his Officers to break them; It was upon the beſt information, I can get, briefly thus: An Act was obtained enabling Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners to eject ignorant, ſcandalous and inſufficient Miniſters and Schoolmaſters, and to place in their rooms ſuch as ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> be approved of for that high calling or to imploy ſome in an Itenerary way, as ſhould be judged moſt conducible for the ſpreading of the Goſpell. Theſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners vigorouſly put in execution this Act, ſo that in ſome Countries there were not left above 5, or 6, of the old ſtock, few were found fit or willing to be ſettled in the room of the ejected, but many were encouraged
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:99865:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and received maintenance out of the publique treaſury to preach in an Ite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerary way, whoſe labour were ſucceſſful, and Schoolmaſters fearing the Lord were ſetled in all Market Towns, and many conſiderable Pariſhes, the benefit whereof had they been continued, would ſoon have been diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned; but this Powers continuance was onely for 3. years, which expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the <hi>March</hi> before the Parliaments diſſolution. Many clamours (for leſſe was not expected) were againſt thoſe Commiſſioners, and Petitions fomented againſt them by the diſaffected and Malignant party there. So that the Parliament, thought not fit to renew the Act (no other diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement then this the wel-affected in Wales received from them) howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the ſequell declares, that if the Parliament laid their little finger for the cruſhing that ſeed (as his expreſſion is, not to be parrelleld ſince the Primative times) I am ſure he hath laid his loyns, and if their but looking a litle aſquint upon them d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>clared they had no ſpirit to the further work; his ſetting himſelf in direct oppoſition thereunto, demonſtrates what ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit he is acted by; and I doubt not, but the Lord in due time will give a Reſurrection to that ſeed, both there and in other parts of the Nation. And it may not be forgotten, that it being perceived <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> fearing the Lord, and waiting for the ſalvation of Iſrael, that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Parliament were declining in their zeal to and for the Lords Work and Cauſe; they appointed a Meeting at <hi>Alhallows</hi> (and from thence afterwards removed unto <hi>Blackefryers)</hi> once a week) to pray unto the Lord for the pouering out of his ſpirit, the comming of Chriſts kingdome, and the performance of Promiſes and Propheſies relating to the ſame, and conſequently remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving out of the way whatſoever might let, and for the executing his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon Babylon. This Meeting was under the diſcontin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nce of the Parliament; things being reported in the worſt ſence to ſeveral eminent Members thereof, though occaſionally there were reflectings upon them, as a block in the way of the Lords work: but the touching upon their declining was ſo acceptable to him, that he incouraged his O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>s and others to frequent the ſame; and Major <hi>Packer</hi> can tell you, that the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral told him, he was a Rogue and Knave if he did neglect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them; but not long after, when the pride, pompe and avarice of him and his Army, and their ſleepineſſe in the Cauſe of Chriſt came to be touched upon, and toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther therewith a jealouſie that not with a right minde the Parliament had been diſſolved, was diſcovered (as then and ſince appears, there was ground ſufficient for ſuch thoughts) he ſet himſelf in oppoſition to them, not contenting himſelf with railing and reviling ſpeeches againſt the moſt eminent of them (for whom time was he had better words) but declaring that he would have his hands up in their blood to the ſleeves, and would lay down his old bones in oppoſing them, venting many bitter and bite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting reproaches (if not blaſphemies) againſt the Lords Spirit, by which they were acted, calling it the ſpirit of the Devil, the miniſtration of evill
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:99865:5"/>
Angels, a thouſand times worſe than the ſpirit of Antichriſt, though he never went to hear and try, as faithfull friends of his had earneſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired him; and though formerly he had ſo much applauded the meeting, yet now ſayes that from the firſt time of their meeting, the ſpirit of the Devill and not of God acted the ſame; at laſt he ſtirred up the Councell, during the ſitting of the little Parliament to ſend for Mr. <hi>Simpſon,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Feake</hi> by Warrant, who appearing thereunto, no matter being found to make good a charge againſt them, they were for that time diſmiſſed, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is obſervable, that in this meeting Mr. <hi>Feake</hi> with much ſolemnity exhorted that as he ſhould, they alſo would ſo ſpeak and carry themſelves as in the preſence of God, the holy Angels and men, for that which ſhould be ſaid would be recorded in heaven, upon which Mr. <hi>Feake</hi> proceeded to deal faithfully with him (the then General) but was interrupted by him, and charged with falſhood; Mr. <hi>Feake</hi> having among other things mentioned how much he was grieved for him, in tampering with the King, and that ſince <hi>Worceſter</hi> fight the Army minding the dividing the Kings Lands, Houſes and Parks, the ſpirit of Prayer was gone off from them, and that he had obſerved the Lords way in carrying on his work had been to furniſh ſome to one part, and ſome to another part of it; ſome to that in <hi>England,</hi> others to that for <hi>Ireland,</hi> and others for <hi>Scotland;</hi> theſe three things the now called Protector objected againſt, as falſhoods in theſe words, or to this effect: <q>I ſpeake as in the preſence of God, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and men; yea, ſaith he, I call God to record upon your ſoul and mine; yea, I ſpeak it in the Holy Ghoſt that theſe particulars are not true,</q> affirming that he had not ſo much as a thought in him of tamper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the King, whileſt one might to half the length of the Table; though it is well known that he with the Officers of the Army had kept three dayes at <hi>Winſor</hi> to ſhame and humble themſelves for that their evill in the Propoſals they had tendered the King, which was the onely thing Mr. <hi>Feake</hi> mentioned to demonſtrate that their tampering; but beſides this the Lord knows and himſelf knows, that he hath to ſeveral perſons acknowledged what offers he had from the late King, as to Honours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> mentioning a <hi>George</hi> and Blew Ribbon, ſuch ſimple knacks ſutable to King-ſhip or Monarchy, if he would have complied with him, and ſaid that his foot had almoſt ſlipt, and that he had faln into thoſe temptations, but that the Lord delivered him, and ſeemed very much to bleſſe the Lord and rejoyce therein, whereby it plainly appears, he had not only thoughts of ſo doing, but did really tamper with him, which of neceſſity muſt hold longer than whileſt one might go the length of the longeſt Table in <hi>England;</hi> with the like confidence he affirmed, that the ſpirit of Prayer was not gone off from the Officers, or that they had ſo minded their arrears, though the eminents for godlineſſe amongſt them frequently be meaned it, that their meeting to ſeek and ſerve the Lord had been neglected; and for
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99865:6"/>
their minding their arrears, ſure it will not need that more words ſhould be uſed, their preſent poſſeſſions ſufficiently demonſtrate; nor will any of them that have but the leaſt ſpark of ingenuity deny the ſame. And for the third particular, ſayes he, you mean my Lord <hi>Fairefax</hi> (though Mr. <hi>Feake</hi> affirmed, he did not think of him, or had he any individuall in his eye) he good man (as his expreſſion was) by reaſon of his many bodily infirmities, and upon no other account declined that ſervice. But thoſe of the old Parliament who attended that godly renowned Perſon (for whoſe faithfulneſſe and uſefulnes the Lord is ever thankfully to be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged) are able to affirm his anſwer to be to this effect. That he looked upon the People of <hi>Scotland</hi> againſt whom they were to ingage, as having many godly amongſt them, and that willingly he would not have his hand in the blood of any ſuch; nevertheleſſe did conceive that the Parliament were the Lords people, and might be carrying on the cauſe of God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he ſhould gladly have been further ſerviceable; but that the Lord did very much cut him ſhort of ſpirit for that work, which (in humility) he conceived was, that ſome more worthy than he, who would bring more glory to God might be imployed in it; and that all might know, the work was Gods, and no mans, former experiences were ſufficient to evidence that, if he had been ſatisfied in his minde, bodily infirmities (under which he had laboured in the moſt of the War) would not have hindred his proceedings: This is the more largely expreſſed, becauſe he hath been fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently found in high aſſeverations, whereby he uſed to obtain credit, when its to be feared, he little conſiders what he ſpeaks; and at this time he had alſo prepared an Auditory of Aldermen, Citizens, Miniſters, and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of the Army, who doubtleſs (there not being time given to open this as now it is) went away taking for granted, that Mr. <hi>Feake</hi> had been left to ſpeak vainly and unadviſedly in theſe things; and there was and is cauſe to think that ſo ſolemn an appeal as this of his was, when he ſhould ſay he ſpeaks in the holy Ghoſt, and yet ſpeaks falſly, will not fall to the ground. And is not his profeſſion of love to thoſe he now perſecutes and impriſons a proof of his readineſſe to proteſt and affirm, what yet he hath little min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, for did he weigh what he ſayes, how durſt he boaſt, he loves ſome of them as his own ſoul; and yet when no crime is objected (though indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours were not wanting by his own inſtruments to have drawn them, as others have been into their ſnares and intanglements) ſeparates them from the fellowſhip of Saints and other dear relations, hurrying them to remote and obſcure Priſons, without giving them notice to accommodate for the ſame, or let any know whether they were to go, though the tender yoak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellow of one of them was at that time in hourly expectation to be brought to bed, which more then in humane carriage [had not the Lord mercifully prevented) might have produced (as it greatly indangered) the death of Mother and Child; is it a fruit of ſuch love to be feaſting at Hampton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>court
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:99865:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Hamman</hi> like, <hi>Eſter.</hi> 3. 15. the ſame day he ſends them to priſon, and doth not the removal of M. G. <hi>Harriſon</hi> from <hi>Portland</hi> where the Governor ſhewed him common reſpect) to the Iſle of Wight (as hath been boaſted for his better accommodation) ſpring from the ſame root ſeeing that ſince his comming thither, he might not receive a Letter from any or ſend ſo much as to his own wife, and this by ſpecial inſtructions from Court unleſſe the Officer there have the peruſal of it, and his wife com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to viſite him (beſides other great incivilities to her as well as him from the Commander there) muſt not ſtir out of the Caſtle until ſhe will go for good and all, or a ſervant to go forth to bring in neceſſarys or any friend ſpeak with him but under a guard.</p>
            <p>Is the adding of Banniſhment to Mr. <hi>Rogers</hi> his bonds after more then 12. months cauſeleſſe Impriſonment, when his wife being but three dayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore delivered of Childe, lying weak of a Feaver, a fruit of ſuch love; what Goſpel-rule is there for ſuch expreſſions of Love? did the primitive Saints ſo manifeſt theirs? but the Scripture ſaith your Brethren that hated you caſt you out for my names ſake, &amp;c. <hi>Eſaiah</hi> 66. 5. if they proceed to lay violent hands on, and beat their fellow ſervants, though they pretend to be brethren (yet the hol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſpirit (who beſt knows their deceitfull hearts) affirms they hate them, and though his words at ſome times, and to ſome perſons be ſmoother and ſofter than Butter and Oyle; yet War and a drawn ſword is in his heart: therefore at other times (for he can change his language <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> company <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> occaſion ſerves) he hath given his mouth to evill, and his tongue to ſlander, reproach and revile thoſe whom yet he will call Chriſtian friends and brethren. What ſhall we ſay to theſe thing he who time was (none more than he) quickned and invited others in ſtreights (and when the Lords work laboured under many dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties) to aſſemble together to ſeek the Lord, is of a ſudden grown jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of all ſuch meetings, and gives occaſion for the greateſt ſcandall that ever was upon them, as if their tendency were onely to ſedition, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of acknowledging the Lord and waiting for his councel, Juntoes are held for the carrying on things according to the craft, wiſdome and poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the world; It is termed no leſſe than Hypocriſie in the little Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ſet apart and keep dayes of Humiliation within themſelves; and when any met more privately, as ſome did, that is branded with diviſion and carrying on deſignes, and this even to this day with more then ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary confidence urged as true: May it not be feared that none would ſo report of and ſuſpect others, but ſuch as had themſelves abuſed the bleſſed ways and ordinances of God to bring about their own contrivances; and if this ſhould be ſo, ſooner or later they will feel and others ſhall ſee that God will not be mocked, who will bring hidden things to light, which is the joy of the upright, but the hypocrites fear. Now conſidering what comlineſs the Lords work had put upon this man, his great aptneſſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive by his plauſible way of ſpeaking, the high profeſſion he made, and his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:99865:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
too frequent calling God to witneſſe, in all which moſt good men were more ready to condemn themſelves than ſuſpect him; it is no leſſe then a very good finger of the Lord, that ſo far makes him manifeſt, as by the few forementioned particulars, though but as it were a comparing himſelf with himſelf, and that there hath been more rottennes in his way than any man (moſt curiouſly obſerving the ſame) is able to hold forth, The all-ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God who ſearcheth and revealeth ſecrets, ſeemeth to declare, in as much as he hath moſt evidently turned his hand againſt him in moſt or all things, this man hath ſet his hand unto, ſince his more groſly turning off from the cauſe of God, which by what enſueth may a little appear. The Sandy bottom (his acceſſe to the Government, is grounded upon) being formerly touched, I ſhall here onely mention the aforeſaid in ſignificant reſignation, being in the Preamble of his Oath, laid as the foundation, and indeed that a buſines ſo hatched and continued, and ſo early a comming to the Houſe for a Vote to inveſt the Power in his hands ſhould be fruſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, may not be eſteemed leſſe than a diſappointment upon him from the Lord. And ſeeing alſo in the Preamble of his Oath is alledged, that upon full and mature conſideration had thereof, and by the deſires and advice of Perſons of intereſt and fidelity in this Commonwealth, he had undertaken the government: there is the more ground to conclude, that in this, he and they were much left to themſelves, that proviſion ſhould not be made againſt that law which enacts, The Office, ſtile, power, dignity, or Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of King in this Nation, ſhall not reſide in or be exerciſed by any ſingle Perſon, and makes it treaſon for any by force of Arms or otherwiſe to be ayding or aſſiſting to any perſons, that ſhall by any way or means be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting any to that Office, but the ſame remains and was a law in force when he lifted up his hand unto the Lord, that he would govern thereby.</p>
            <p>And may it not be feared, that he rather deſigned to arrogate to himſelf the glory of theſe ſuceſſes at <hi>Dunbar</hi> and <hi>Worceſter,</hi> both given upon the 3. of <hi>Septemb.</hi> (the latter whereof when ſtanders by, knew not the meaning of it, he tearmed the crowning mercy) rather then to give the ſame unto the Lord from whom they came, otherwiſe he would have remembred to have kept holy this day, which without due reſpect unto him, he aſſigned for the aſſembling his Parliament, the prophanation and prophaners of which day have been generally overtaken with ſignal judgments; and it was obſerved that the late King ſuffered in his reputation amongſt the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber people of this Nation, and was ever on the declining hand from the time of his manifeſt neglect of that day. Who may not ſee that the Lord blaſted this mans expectations from his Parliament, ſo on that day aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, to whom in his firſt Speech, he ſayes, That to ſee a free Parliament, he had deſired as his life, and to keep them ſo, ſhould be more then his life; and yet ſome faithfull Patriots, but uſing freedome in debate, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Parliamentary Priviledge he takes notice of, upon the 9. day (for
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:99865:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
wonders are not of long continuance) though ſworn not to imploy the <hi>Militia</hi> (the Parliament ſitting) without their Conſent, contrary to that Oath, and thoſe high profeſſions; he locks up the door of the Houſe, and by his Souldiers keeps out thoſe that will not comply with his intereſt. And was it not the Lords doing though the Houſe was ſo garbled, whereby at leaſt two part of three were his Councel, Allyes, Officers, and their relations; yet ſhould not confirm his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the onely and chief thing he aymed at; And no leſſe is the Lord to be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged in turning their edge againſt himſelf, who had ſo much irritated them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe, whom he tearmes the Fifth Monarchy men, a praying faithful (though a deſpiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d) people, whoſe chiefeſt crime occaſioning his rage upon ſuch, will be found witneſſing for the work of the Lord againſt his Apoſtacy and Uſurpation. To whoſe eare in Europe hath not the report reached of the Lords lifted up hand againſt him in the <hi>India</hi> undertaking, which is the more to be noted by us, in regard that he and all his Courtiers, upon all occaſions boaſted of it, as that whereby it ſhould appear he had not Apoſtatized, but effectually in the moſt prudent and beſt way was carrying on the Cauſe againſt the common enemy, which others by their giddineſs would have diſhonored and loſt. And that none might ſhare with him in the honour of it, even his garbled Parliament (without whom they ſitting nothing of that kind ought to have been done) by the old tricks of the Courtiers comming earlier than uſuall to the Houſe, muſt Vote (upon pretence of keeping under ſecre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie) the management of that Expedition to him and his Councel, who were not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wanting to make all neceſſary Proviſions for ſuch an undertaking, and might well conclude (as they did) ſucceſſe anſwerable to what their hearts could deſire, unleſſe being faln under the Lords diſpleaſure their diſappointment ſhould be, (as by a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle from him.) His Fleet and Forces go forth with all renown of former ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes and victories reputation, of wiſdome, courage and valour; and at their firſt arrivall before St. <hi>Domingo,</hi> the place deſigned to be poſſeſſed, the inhabiting Span<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard ſtruck with terrour, for ſake the town for 3 days together, this advantage not being improved, they take courage and return for the defence of it. Near 10000. men are landed who marching towards it are incountred, repulſed by about 300. a ſecond attempt is made, and again they are put to flight, and near 1000. ſlain by fifty poor <hi>Negroes,</hi> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fidels and Idolaters, which in a ſence may be called the people of Gods curſe. Having in theſe incounters and by ſickneſſe loſt neer 3000. men or more, and ſo diſmaid, as that the ſhaking of the leaves, and the noiſe of Crabs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come an affrighting to them, all courage and wiſdome being taken from them, quitting <hi>Hiſpaniola</hi> they reimbarque for <hi>Jamaica,</hi> where they are ſure to meet with no oppoſition; but what be the Lords further pleaſure concerning them is yet hid from us, onely note, ſoon after their arrival there, one of their Ships, which had in her greateſt ſtore of proviſions is ſet on fire, conſumed and loſt, and in return of part of the Fleet for <hi>England,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Vice-Admiral, a Ship of the 2 d. rank periſhes in the Sea by fire, with about 150 men in her, ſo as the common Sea-men did obſerve and ſay, ſure this was no other then the Lords own finger againſt them; the certain account of Gods blaſting this expedition thus miraculouſly (ſo contrary to what he at the putting on of his Harneſs, had ſo vainly boaſted off) was brought unto him, when he was ſpeaking Peace and ſafety; and that none ſhould make him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:99865:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
having broke in pieces the plots (as they are called at Court) that were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him by ſome Officers of the Armies of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> of the Fleet, and that of the Caveleers; whereupon he vaunted, abuſing that word, That no weapon for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med againſt him ſhould proſper: whereas it is conjectured, that the contrivance and management of the foreſaid attempts were his own deſignes, and acted by ſome of his own Agents; at the ſame time alſo he had ſecured ſuch of the 5th Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy-men (ſo called) of whom he had any jealouſie, or could not be drawn to ſerve his luſt; and having now (ſelf-denyingly) diſpoſed the government of <hi>Ireland</hi> to his ſon <hi>Henry</hi> (none like him for ſuch a truſt;) and that of <hi>Scotland</hi> alſo in hands fitted to anſwer his ends; it remained only, that he ſhould make himſelf Lord Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount, King or Emperor over the whole, and the ſucceſſion in his heirs; for co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour whereof a Petition was carrying on in the Army, City, and diverſe Countries, yea, in Priſons. All which well becomes him, that hath not ſtuck to ſay of Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as <hi>Luther</hi> of covetouſneſſe, The Devill had never tempted him to it; yea, that he could ſay in the ſame ſpirit <hi>David</hi> did. He was not puft in minde, he was as a weaned childe, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aught not high things. Now doth not this ſo ſignal a fruſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his hopes, give us grounds to judg that the Lord hath ſet himſelf againſt him for evill, and this being a ſtroak of his ſending, there ſhall be found no healing of it, which through the pride and ſtoutneſs of his heart, he will not ſee nor acknowledg but ſayes, He will repair the fallen Bricks with Free-ſtone, the Cicamore with Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dars. And as <hi>Baalam</hi> did beat his Aſſe though the Angel withſtood him, he impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons the inſtrument, <hi>Venables</hi> and <hi>Penn</hi> (who formerly whileſt in the Lord work were found faithfull and often bleſſed with ſucceſſe) as if the miſcarriage had been through their treachery, when every eye may ſee, it was from God, who withheld wiſdome and courage; but whileſt his Phyſitians are applying plaſters, and he is licking himſelf whole, Gen. <hi>Blake</hi> (which few have obſerved as they ſhould) miſſing the Proviſions ſent to enable his continuance out, untill he ſhould meet with and catch the Spaniſh Plate fleet (for which he had waited ſome time) returning empty handed. And thus when there is none ſhut up or left the mighty Lord, the Lord of hoſts pleads the cauſe of his people, giving him a miſcarrying wombe, and dry breaſts, and ſo blaſts him in both the ends of the earth, whereunto he had ſpread his wings to get name and fame, by two ſuch Fleets, as ſcarce ever any King of <hi>England</hi> had at once upon the Seas; the charge of which Expedition a Million of mony did not deſray. At laſt gold and ſilver every way fayling, we have an acknowledgment in the Preamble of his declaration for a Faſt, that rebukes from God are upon him, but thoſe for the evill and apoſtacy of others; not giving glory to God in confeſſing his own, and adding to this his riotous Feaſting, and as is boaſted with rare Muſick, entertaining the Popiſh Ambaſſador of France, the day ſeven night before his faſt, which is far from telling the Nations the Lord hath founded <hi>Zion,</hi> and the poor 'of his people ſhall truſt in it, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14 32. Is there not ſtrong ground of jealouſie miniſtred to fear, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> heart is hardened rather than humbled under the Lords mighty hand, who aſſuredly will not be mocked by him; and its to be hoped, his People will not be further deluded; for can any reaſonably think, the War brought upon us from <hi>Spaine,</hi> which his luſt provoked unto, and for which the anger of the Lord hath ſo ſmoaked againſt him, is (as in his Declaration, he would perſwade)
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:99865:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
principally for the advancement of the kingdome of Chriſt, when at the ſame time, which is worthy obſervation, he makes Peace with <hi>France,</hi> a popiſh Nation, guilty of much blood of Saints, the forces within whoſe territories (among others) ſo late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and barbarouſly embrued their hands in the blood of the poore <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> and by whoſe Ambaſſadour ſuch grievous condition hath been obtruded on the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of them. Having thus opened the foregoing particulars, ſome whereof were not ſo generally known; and others (its to be doubted) not ſo duly obſerved, I ſhall now for the ſake of thoſe who would not be ſwayed by their fond affections, but their judgements grounded upon the word of truth, which is able to make the man of God perfect readily furniſhed to every good work, preſent a few ſcriptures which if the Lord pleaſe to open by his ſpirit (the beſt interpreter) may be of further uſe unto them. <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.18.</bibl> If I build again the things deſtroyed, I make my ſelf a tranſgreſſor.</q> 
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 31.1.</bibl> Wo to them that go down to Aegypt for help, and ſtay on horſes, and truſt on charriots, becauſe they are many; and in horſmen, becauſe they very ſtrong; but they look not to the holy one of Iſrael, neither ſeek the Lord.</q> Read <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.3 firſt <hi>verſes,</hi> 
               <q>They take councel but not of me, and cover with a coveting, but not of my ſpirit.</q> 
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Hab.</hi> 2. 9.</bibl> Wo to him that coveteth an evill, covetouſnes to his houſe, that he might ſet his neſt on high. <bibl>
                     <hi>v.</hi> 6.</bibl> Wo to him that encreaſeth that that is not his, how long; and to him that ladeth himſelf with thick clay. <bibl>
                     <hi>v.</hi> 15.</bibl> Wo to him that giveth his neighbour drink, that putteſt thy bottle to him and makeſt him drunken alſo.</q> 
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Hoſ</hi> 8.3.</bibl> Iſrael hath caſt off the thing that is good, the enemy ſhal purſue him. <bibl>
                     <hi>v.</hi> 4</bibl> They have ſet Kings but not by me, they have made Princes and I knew it not.</q> 
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Amos</hi> 6. 1.</bibl> Wo to them that are at eaſe in Sion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>v.</hi> 3.</bibl> Ye that put far away the evill day, and cauſe the ſeat of violence to come near. <bibl>
                     <hi>v.</hi> 4.</bibl> That lie upon beds of ivory, and ſtretch themſelves upon their couches, and eat the lamb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> out of the flock, and the calves out of the midſt of the ſtall. <bibl>
                     <hi>v.</hi> 5.</bibl> That chant to the ſound of the Viol, and invent themſelves inſtruments of muſick like <hi>David;</hi> that drink wine in bowls, anointing themſelves with the chief ointments; but they are not grieved for the afflictions of <hi>Joſeph.</hi> 
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>v.</hi> 12.</bibl> For ye have turned judgment into Gall, and the fruit of righteouſnes into H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mlock. <bibl>
                     <hi>v.</hi> 13.</bibl> Ye which rejoyce in a thing of nought, which ſay, have we not taken horns unto us by our own ſtrength.</q> 
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5.6, 7.</bibl> They ſhall go with their flocks and their herds to ſeek the Lord, but they ſhall not find him, he hath withdrawn himſelf from them; they have dealt treacherouſly with the Lord, for they have begotten ſtron children. Now ſhall a month devour them with their portions.</q> 
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65. 11.</bibl> But ye are they that forſake the Lord, that forget my holy mountain, that prepare a table for that troop, and that furniſh a drink offering for that number; therefore will I number you, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> 
               <hi>v.</hi> 12, 13, 14, 15, compared with <hi>cap.</hi> 66 <hi>v.</hi> 3, 4, 5, 6. <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29. 15.</bibl> Wo to them that ſeek deep to hide their councel from the Lord, &amp; their works arein the dark; and they ſay, who ſeeth us and who knoweth; ſurely your turning things upſide down ſhall be eſteemed as the potters clay, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>v.</hi> 21.</bibl> That make a man an offender for a word, and lay a ſnare for him hat reproveth in the gate; and turn a ſide the juſt for a thing of nought.</q> 
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 48.</bibl> But and if that evill ſervant ſhall ſay in his heart, my Lord delayeth his comming, and ſhall begin to ſmite his fellow ſervant, and to eat and drink with the drunken, the Lord of that ſervant ſhall come in a day when he
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:99865:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
looked not for him, and in an houre that he is not aware of, and ſhall cut him in ſunder, and appoint him his portion with the hypocrites.</q> 
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.8.</bibl> Now go write it before them in a Table, and note it in a Book, that it may be for a time to come for ever and ever.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>[Reader, wanting room at preſent you may pleaſe to reade th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſcriptures in order at large, as they ſtand, for they ſhould have come in here: viz Iſai.</hi> 30 <hi>v.</hi> 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17. and 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36. <hi>v.</hi> 16. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26. 11. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14. 6. and <hi>Prov.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 24, 25, 26, 27, 28.]</p>
            <p>If that which is written be for our learning, then where we finde like ſins, we may with ſobriety &amp; humble reverence apply ſuch judgments and ſentences to them as the holy ſpirit in the ſcripture hath given in like caſes; if it was ſo fatall to <hi>Pharaoh</hi> though a heathen for not letting Gods people go free (he being come down to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them, <hi>Exo.</hi> 3. 8.) as brought upon him all thoſe ſore plagues; if God reckoned the Amalekites interruption, becauſe he had begun to deliver his people, a laying their hands upon his throne, <hi>Exod.</hi> 17. 16. And therefore would have war with them for ever. <hi>If</hi> God was ſo angry with the Congregation of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when they but ſpake of making them a Captain to go back into Aegypt, whileſt their chief Leaders mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before him for the ſame. <hi>Num.</hi> 14.4, 5, 6. 32 37. What ſhall we ſay of the preſent tranſgreſſions, when after the mighty God hath bowed the heavens, and may be ſaid to have come down, as in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64. 13. after he hath begun to deliver his people out of Aegyptian bondage, even to the drowning of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his hoſt, when the Captain of the Lords Army, the General himſelf, ſhall not onely return to Aegypt, but beat them of the congregation, that will not return with him, having thereby, brought ſo evill report upon that good land (to wit) the glorious Cauſe of God and his Chriſt, that the wiſdome, powerfulnes and love of God (which were fairly written upon his late works) the Kingdom of Chriſt and his poore people waiting for the ſame, were never under ſo great a reproach; too many now queſtioning whither there be either God, Chriſts Cauſe or People, or all be not a deviſed fable, onely for men to attain their luſts by. Seeing then things revealed belong to us, and where we finde on the houſe top breach of Promiſe lying, hypocriſie and perjury, departing away from God, hating of brethren which is Murder. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 15.) Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, Revolt, Perſecution, love of this world and the things of it, where judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is turned backward, where juſtice ſtandeth a far off; where truth is fallen, where equity cannot enter; yea he that departeth from evil and will teſtifie for good, maketh himſelf a prey; I ſay of ſuch perſons and their things, Gods people are taught by <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, by Chriſt and his Apoſtles how to judge of them, that their way is diſpleaſing to the Lord, they are enemies to the Croſſe of Chriſt, a ſhameful ſpuing will come upon all their glory. Therefore all that love their God, their own ſouls, &amp; the good of their own Country, ought to depart from the tents of ſuch men, leaſt by their complyance, that wo of calling evill good befall them, &amp; ſo pertaking in a meaſure of their ſins, they partake in their plagues alſo; Rather if the God of all grace ſo pleaſe; and oh that it might ſeem good in his ſight, that judgment might return unto righteouſneſſe, and that all of each judgment, that are upright in ſoule with one heart might follow hard after the ſame.</p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
